[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software hello or software
engineering radio this is Robert bloomin
today this will be a different kind of
episode there have been a lot of changes
in the show over the last two years
instead of bringing you a normal show I
wanted to take some time and to tell you
where we've been and where we're going
later on in the episode I will be
talking to members of the team who
produced the shows and the people behind
the scenes who helped put it online I
will do my section as a monologue and
the others will be interviews and if you
don't like this show don't worry because
the next time we'll be back to our
regular format let's start by talking
about the history of the show the show
was founded in 2006 we're now well into
our 10th year which is really old for a
podcast there was hardly anything going
on in the podcast world 2006 by the time
that you listen to this we will have
published over 230 shows the show was
started by Marcus voltar computer
science researcher and practitioner in
Germany the show was at the time
probably the first podcast dealing with
software engineering topics one of our
hosts told me that he had declined the
invitation to get involved with the show
because he didn't really expect
podcasting would would ever take off but
he did eventually join the show started
and has always been a volunteer project
very much like an open source project
Marcus and the founders continued to run
the show completely volunteer until
February of 2012 that time Marcus handed
the show over to the I Triple E Computer
Society under the umbrella
of the Society's print magazine known as
software the magazine itself has
recently gone all digital and it
continues to be the sponsor of the show
the show hosts are still all volunteer
but we have employees at the I Triple E
Computer Society spend some of their
time on the publishing side to get the
show edited and uploaded to the web I
got involved with the show in 2010 my
very first episode was number 157 on
Hadoop with Philips ilogger the way this
came about is my friend Charles Anderson
who is now show host told me about this
show how great it was and he recommended
that I listen to it I started browsing
through the website and there were
dozens or a hundred or more episodes
that I wanted to listen to I downloaded
many episodes on to my huge portable
media player that had a hard drive and I
spent maybe a year listening to episodes
in the back catalogue I have not
listened to every single episode but I
have listened to everyone since mid-2009
and about 85% of the ones maybe 90% of
the ones before that on one of the
episodes they asked for volunteers I
responded I did a test show which was
accepted and I became a host being a
host it's been a lot of fun and that's
why I'm still doing it now after several
years I like producing content I like
educating people and one of the great
things you get about being a host is you
get to talk to all these experts about
things and ask some where ever you want
to know which there's really no other
way to do that other than being in media
the show has made a difference for me in
my career and I hope that as for the
listeners as well one of the principles
established by Markus is every episode
should combine specifics about a
particular topic along with some general
permanent computer science or software
engineering concepts we are not trying
to be the show about what happened in
the last five or 10 minutes we're trying
to create content that will be useful
for people even years in the future and
even to some extent of people stopped
using a particular technology that was
featured in the show we want people to
listen to the new episodes but I
encourage listeners to go back and do as
I did listen to the back catalog we on
the show take a lot of pride in how
relevant the Epis are so it's are even
years after they're published we look at
download statistics from one of the
services in our publication platform
showing usually about 15,000 downloads a
day that episode is published and then
about 1,000 or 2,000 more per month for
several years after that we think that
the surge on the date of publication is
subscriptions people have through RSS
iTunes or services like that and that
those shows maybe auto downloaded but we
we think the ones coming from months or
years later are search results or links
of people forward around it can take us
several years to even really have a good
idea how well a particular show did the
first thing we do on an episode is to
give a biography of the guest I'm gonna
do that for you right now I started out
in physics I got my bachelor's degree at
Stanford University and then I got a
master's in engineering at the
University of California in Berkeley my
first job was computer programming for a
telco and I liked it so I stayed in the
same field and this has been my career
for over 20 years now the field has
changed so much for the better over that
time I wish I had all the tools that we
have now when I got out of school right
now I am employed as a software engineer
and a DevOps at Salesforce in San
Francisco now more about the show when
the I Triple E Computer Society took
over the show it was expected that many
editors within the I Triple E would want
to produce shows but for the most part
that
has not happened in April of 2014
Forrest Scholl who was at the time the
editor of software magazine recognized
that the show needed someone to really
drive it forward and asked me to become
the show editor which I have been doing
for over one year now I will be talking
to Forrest later in this episode right
now I'll talk about what I am trying to
do as this show editor first and
foremost I want to continue the show as
it has been which is a great show about
hardcore Technology and software
engineering founders of the show created
a great format and left us this
fantastic legacy and I hope that we can
continue to live up to that and just
keep it the way it is the 50,000
downloads that we get for an episode
that's a pretty big number for a really
specialized niche topic and it's a high
bar for us to live up to who who are now
running the show since I became the show
editor we've added a number of hosts
when I started there were three active
hosts in that we now have nine which
include myself Everhard
Wolff Jeff Meyerson tobias COTS johannes
tennis stefan till cog Charles Anderson
Josh lon and Sven Johann some of those
had done podcasts before but not for
this show well others were completely
new to podcasting two of the hosts
Stefan and Sven have been guests on the
show before becoming hosts after adding
a host I've been focusing on
organizational improvements to get the
new hosts trained on how to do an
episode I created a manual we are going
to be open sourcing the show host manual
sometime this year manual provides the
detailed instructions on how we create
an episode I have shown it to some
people in the publications and media
field and gotten some feedback we hope
that others in the podcasting and
technical publications area will also
find it useful there will be an
announcement on the show or the blog or
somewhere Twitter when this happens next
I'm gonna say a bit about how we do an
episode
the first step is someone comes up with
an idea or maybe a guest or both
whichever one then you need the other
you need a topic and a guest so we ask
the guest if he or she will come on and
when the guest agrees then we start
working on show development some of the
topics come from me but I can really
only suggest the topics if a host likes
a topic he will do it if the host has a
better idea he'll go with his own topic
once we have the topic and the guest the
host writes an outline this is where
most of the work comes in if the host is
not already an expert on the topic and
and most of us are not experts on most
of the things we do shows about because
that would be too many things for any
one person to be an expert on then the
host has to learn something about the
topic we're not trying to become experts
but you need to know enough to have an
intelligent discussion with the guest
who is an expert then we go through a
collaborative editing process the host
puts his outline up on a Google Doc and
all those two have the chance to review
and comment on it once that gets revised
and finalized then ready to record the
interview there's a ton of stuff we've
all been learning about how to make a
good recording overall the standards in
the podcast space are constantly rising
audio quality is overall across podcasts
higher now than it's ever been we will
not ever have studio quality audio for
every show unless barring some
improvements in technology because most
of our shows are recorded over the
Internet we have had poor audio quality
on some shows and we are working to get
up to at least adequate quality on every
throw through a combination of hardware
software configuration and processing
improvements we we do recognize that a
lot of people listen while they're on
the bus outside doing tours and there
needs to be a decent clear signal
without a lot of
noise so that people can listen to the
show now when it comes to doing the
interview the host goes into the
interview with an outline but the
outline is not completely fixed
structure it gives you an idea of what
you're going to talk about it gives you
a map of where you want to go but things
never go exactly the way you've outlined
and that's often for a good reason which
is the guest maybe says something that's
more interesting than what you are going
to ask and I encourage those if the
guest says something interesting then go
with that and you always have the
outline to fall back on if you need to
know what your next question is so
there's no there's no perfect balance
between the planned and unplanned
content that's part of the art of being
a host is when to go off the map and
when to get back on it the time
management aspect is also very important
you the listener have given us an hour
of your time and we want to use that
hour very well we can't cover everything
there is to know about a topic in an
hour so the host has to think about what
is really the most important part of
this topic what do I want to ensure that
I cover within one hour it's okay to
change your mind if something better
comes along but definitely by the end of
the hour you should have covered all of
the things that you think are important
and give the guest some time to talk
about where to learn more a lot of our
interviews are recorded on skype some of
them are in person but quite often the
hosting guests have no way to be in the
same place at the same time and
sometimes are on different continents
yo.hannes produced an episode number 215
where the hosts and guests on three
different continents that was quite a
miracle of time management and
scheduling in the early years the VoIP
technology was not reliable enough to
use for recording shows so we did record
them all in person on pretty high
quality gear as VoIP has become more
reliable we are doing more and more
shows on skype which is great from an
access standpoint it allows us to talk
to the
we could never otherwise talk to but the
audio quality is definitely lower on
skype then at the present time lower on
skype then than it is face to face with
professional gear we are watching some
technologies that are not ready for
production yet that are trying to solve
this problem and we will follow that
space with great interest
once episode is recorded the show writes
some show notes links and we hand it off
to the media production team at the
Computer Society Brian Brennan who I was
speaking to later manages that part of
the process a group of people who do
audio editing and publications clean up
the audio do the leveling format it down
mix it to mono and put it up to the
website having this type of professional
support has been a huge benefit for this
show when I first joined I had to spend
several hours editing each show and we
had volunteers who did the publication
having a group of people that do all
this has made it possible for the hosts
to really focus on producing content
which is what we're good at
and it reduces the learning curve of
learning about audio technology in order
to become a content producer after we
publish an episode we all discuss the
show among the hosts the members of the
team other than the hosts give the host
feedback on what we liked what we didn't
and what could have been better we're
all trying to learn as a team and grow
and become better show producers and who
better to give us feedback than other
show producers historically we've
averaged about two shows per month over
the 10 years in 2013 and the first half
of 2014 the publication frequency
dropped to about 1 per month and since I
came on and added new hosts who are back
up to a little bit more than 2 per month
as we close out 2015 in the second half
of the year we plan to increase
publication frequency in the range of 3
for per month in this second half of
2015 I may add one more show host this
is something you're interested in then
please reach out to me by email or
Twitter or on LinkedIn in 2016 if we can
get everything working we would like to
go to a weekly show and that would be my
goal for us to publish weekly throughout
2016 like anything else a podcast needs
to grow and change the current team
wants to keep bringing you great shows
about some of our traditional areas like
programming languages databases and
operating systems we also want to branch
out and this is not totally new for the
show but we want to do a bit more on
career and cultural aspects of the
software engineering field we had two
great episodes of 2014 with Tobias
Scott's talking to Randy Shoop about job
interviews and company culture we have
some other show ideas about career
strategies and related areas if you have
any ideas please feel free to suggest
them to us on any of our media channels
last year I started writing a column
about a single episode of this show for
the I Triple E computer society's
software magazine the column contains a
2,000 word excerpt from the transcript
of one of the episodes which is about 10
minutes of air time the column used to
be available only to subscribers of the
print edition but it is now outside the
paywall magazine has gone all digital
the magazine is published six times per
year for the magazine column episodes we
will publish the entire transcript on
our blog we'd love to publish
transcripts of every episode but we are
currently not able to do that that's
something that I'm hoping will find a
way to accomplish maybe next year if
anyone has ideas about transcripts also
please contact me another big goal for
us starting this year has been to reach
out and engage the listeners that's
that's you more
than we have in the past until recently
there were three channels for reaching
us email comments on our blog and
writing a review on iTunes the email
address was broken for a while when we
switched hosts but that's working again
and it is team @ SC - radio dotnet
iTunes review still work but that has
not been very popular with listeners
very few people have chosen that format
so we are trying other channels we're
now active on all of the major social
networks our Twitter handle is at SC
Radio know - you can follow us there you
can retweet favorite or direct message
us Jeff Meyerson is running a Facebook
page which is called software
engineering radio be sure to look for
the Facebook page not the Facebook group
there is a defunct Facebook group called
Software Engineering radio to be as
Scott's is leading our group on Google+
by the same name I organized a group on
LinkedIn with the same exact name as
well you can find us on any of these
sites or groups by searching for
software engineering radio please follow
us on any of these platforms and use
them to communicate with us starting
with show - 18 this year we pre announce
the upcoming episodes on these social
platforms another small change in our
messaging is the new logo this was
designed for us by show P massive
ar-rahmani and we're using it on all of
our properties to have a consistent
graphical image we would love to hear
from you the listeners tell us how we're
doing what did you like and not like
about a single episode or the show in
general we promise to read everything
and to respond if you ask a question or
want a response you can also reach out
to individual hosts who are all over the
web on different social networks you can
find our individual contact details on
the team page on the website SC deonette
and now I am going to wrap up my part of
show you will next hear an interview
that I have done with each one of the
hosts and the management team I'm gonna
start with an interview that I recorded
in mid-2014 with a Marcus voltar I had
planned to do this episode sometime in
soon after that recording but things
happened and I had to deal with other
things get hosts on board so I decided
to wait so this interview is about a
year old but I wanted you to hear it
anyway just keep in mind it's it's
slightly dated hope that you liked this
episode and all of us hope to hear from
you for software engineering radio this
has been Robert blumen I'm now joined by
Marcus voltar for a longtime listeners
Marcus needs no introduction for those
of you who joined more recently Marcus
was the founder of the program and was
involved in over a hundred and twenty
episodes Marcus welcome back to software
engineering radio hello thanks for
having me think people would like to
know how did the show get started
well I'm it's long time ago it was in
2006 I'm not a hundred percent sure but
what I do remember is that I started
listening to a podcast security now this
week in tech legal up hard stuff and I
was thinking that this podcast thing is
great and and that I would like to
listen to some really interesting
software engineering stuff and I looked
through iTunes and other places and it
didn't find anything and so then I
thought well if there isn't anything
then I need to write it and so then I
talked to a couple of friends I'll tell
about Alexander Schmidt think that was
the core group I probably missed
somebody sorry for that and they agreed
to join and then we started I guess that
was that was the story in your time
doing the show which now has over 200
episodes do any memories stand out what
really does stand out is I go to a lot
of conferences and you know present
tutorials and stuff like that and for a
time I I always took my recording gear
so I can interview people at these
conferences and so I I do remember
frantically looking for quiet spots and
talking to the organizers in his hands
and trying to find rooms and organize
rooms and trying to find people so that
was quite
I didn't you know I didn't see much of
the out of the rest of the conference
because I spent most of the time
interviewing people and I do remember
that one of the episodes one of my
favorite episodes was with dick Gabriel
on Lisp but that was that was one of
these conference recordings so that was
that was a lot of fun but many others
were fun as well but I don't remember
it's a while ago
what podcasts do you listen to you now
it's a long list so I still listen to
security now I still listen to some of
the other twit podcasts I do listen to a
couple of German podcasts someone on
science there is a few nice science
podcasts I do listen to a few aviation
podcasts there are a few interesting
American or English language science
podcasts but most of them are in this
typical American style you know a lot of
blah blah not that much content
sorry Americans but you know the style
right it's bit different then then maybe
what Europeans perhaps typically do and
that's mostly what I listen to
well maybe you're influenced but in
software engineering radio we strive to
have a lot of content that is true and I
really do appreciate that of course it's
important when you do a podcast that the
personalities behind the show become
visible and so small talk and and
emotions are important Marcus thank you
so much for letting software engineering
radio catch up with you thank you what's
a pleasure my next guest is one of our
hosts Everhard wolf Everhard welcome to
software engineering radio thanks iRobot
hi every heart let's start out where do
you live as - Berlin Germany the the
capital and that's also where I do most
of my work and what type of work do you
do so I'm a consultant and trainer so I
convert people concerning sofas texture
and modern I script approaches like no
sequel cloud and things like micro
services things of that nature and what
else about your background would you
like those things you know I have a
pretty strong background in in spring so
I work for Springs with the sauce at one
point and I'm also a Java champion so I
do quite a lot of stuff
chiming Java just wrote a book about
continuous delivery in German I'm afraid
so that's basically what I'm doing
and my goal concerning se radio is well
to give people the opportunity to
improve their skills concerning software
engineering and architecture and have
some fun doing so so that's basically
what I'm doing and that's also why I'm
writing a few articles and I'm also at
several conferences I'm also in the
program committee of some conferences so
that's how I try to to sort of help
others improve you've been with the show
since very early on tell us how you got
started with the show and and what's it
been like over a number of years now
yeah so basically when Marcus started
the show um he asked me whether I wanted
to join and I really feel if felt
honored to do so I enjoyed it quite a
lot at that time and did some some nice
shows about it Marcus was really the
driving force behind the thing and I'm
quite thankful that he started the
little thing and it has always been a
fun part I think and it has always been
I'm quite surprised how much the team
can actually put together and and the
quality of the other thing so that's why
I enjoy it enjoy it a lot
great thank you so much for everything
you do for this show and for doing this
interview yeah thank you for all the
bark that you're investing in the
podcast my next guest is Charles
Anderson the interest of disclosure I
should say that Charles and I have been
friends for many years and he was one of
the people that I reached out to to join
me as a host when I came on as editor
start with where do you live I live in
on a farm actually outside of Monmouth
Oregon which is outside of Salem Oregon
which is the state capital and that's
south of Portland Oregon which is sort
of what most people know of
in terms of war again so depending on
where I'm trying to get to in Portland I
may be an hour and a half away from
Portland okay and that's the west coast
of the United States for some of our
international listeners so tell the
listeners about your background sure I
studied computer science at the
University of California Berkeley I
worked in Silicon Valley and the greater
Bay Area for about ten years before I
decided to go back to graduate school I
studied operations research in graduate
school that was again at the University
of California at Berkeley just because I
was too lazy to apply anywhere else and
then sort of after that I worked for
several years here in Oregon at the
Western Oregon University I taught
computer science at the undergraduate
level and then after some sort of life
changes and whatnot I decided to go back
to software development because although
I really liked teaching my real love is
for software development you think your
interest in teaching has any connection
with doing podcasts Oh certainly I see
it as a very similar sort of thing if
for no other reason then you know they
always say that to to really get to know
a topic you need to explain it to
someone else and so whereas I might have
a passable level of interest and
knowledge about a specific topic or
something just for my own purposes but
if I'm gonna go and teach it or discuss
it on a podcast I'm certainly going to
dive into it much more deeply sure
then you've talked about some of the
areas that you studied what are some of
your technical interests besides
operations research let's see I'm
primarily what I
call a back-end or a systems programmer
I like to call it software without a
face so very much involved in things
like databases networking scaling and
even if you will
mundane things like build tools or
testing frameworks again you know that's
things that people don't see for very
specific interests in the field I've
always been very attracted to operating
systems in particular file systems and
databases how long have you been doing
this show and what has it been like
being a show host oh sure yeah as you
mentioned I I started listening I can't
even remember when I started listening
to software engineering radio as many
many years ago might I think somebody on
another podcast had mentioned it and
then I remember I told you about it and
got you hooked on it and next thing I
know you were a host and now the editor
I for me part of part of being on the
show part of I've certainly enjoyed the
opportunity like I mentioned before to
kind of dive into some topics a little
more deeply than I otherwise would have
as you've kind of hinted out there is
kind of a teaching aspect to podcasting
that I enjoy but then another part of it
is is kind of a giving back I feel that
over the years
I've certainly gained a lot of knowledge
and information from podcasts including
software engineering radio and this is
my opportunity to kind of give back so I
really enjoy that great well thank you
for so much for talking to this show
sure thanks my next guest is host Tobia
Scott
Tobias welcome to software engineering
radio thank you very much where do you
live well I live in the western part of
Germany near Cologne which should be no
by people around the world but yeah
that's what I tell but originally I come
from the eastern part of Germany so I've
got a bit of a culture clash - here
within the last two years but it's great
tell the listeners about your background
well my background is I studied computer
science till 2009 and from then on I
worked in different positions being a
software engineer project manager and IT
consultant that's kind of my past yeah
and what do you do for work right now
right now I'm working as a technical
consultant for recombines a company that
is based in San Francisco and they are
doing a lot of self engineering here in
the vine bar near Cologne what are some
of your interests in technology area
well basically it's everything around
cloud technologies and big data which is
some things we had on the show as well
like like micro services and things
around that and all the scaling services
and stuff like this this is kind of
amazingly and hugely pressed by the
technologies that are out there and how
is that been being a host what's it been
like it's a great experience cuz I never
got to know so many people with
different backgrounds and and who are
doing different technologies and
inspiring technologies and have great
ideas like Randi before and it's a great
chance of talking to so many great
people and I loved it it's a lot more
work than I thought it would be but I
enjoy very much and maybe my family
sometimes doesn't but I love it
great thank you very much Tobias thank
you my guest now is Stefan took off
Stefan welcome to the show I'd rather
you the first questions I ask everyone
are where do you live and what do you do
for work
so I live in Germany power with this
very small town between : here and I
have a
you'll roll I am a consultant I work in
projects and software architecture space
typically doing workshops and on-site
trainings and consultants consulting
work as well as being the managing
director of the consultancy itself so
I'd like to say that I spend about half
of my time doing well like and the other
half doing what nobody wants to view
which is a bit of a lie this fits my
interests pretty well in some of your
main interests then would be why so some
for architecture in general is a huge
interest to me because that's obviously
a topic that is that it comes up
everywhere I also have a long history
with distributed computing topics I used
to do a lot of love the very various
things and for example a remote
procedure call of disasters in all their
and all their various forms as well as a
lot of web services which I could
probably count as part of that I also
did a lot of work rest space actually
authored a book in German which I'm now
happy to have a few co-authors for the
third edition which is coming out soon
and the last few years I've come to and
most of my time talking about and
working with web technologies not only
for service use cases those of the
general application use cases in many
different areas so that's my main
interest web technology that's a byte a
wide space you are one of a small number
of people who've been a guest on the
show and a host what's the difference
those are very interesting I think most
people in our industry like to hear
themselves talk I'm no exception
I like expressing my ideas and I love
getting feedback to them but I also
really like talking to interesting
people and just take a step back and
just ask the questions it's very
interesting I can of course I of course
learn a lot or from from the interviews
from the talks that I do because the
guests are interesting to me personally
otherwise I would not want to talk to
them and of course even as an
interviewer it can also steer the
conversation to interesting directions
and help express things even if you do
know something about the topic which is
always the case but sometimes it's
really interesting to hear somebody else
express ideas maybe in a different way
or highlight different aspects of it so
I actually enjoy both and I wouldn't say
that I strongly favor one over the other
when you went from outside to the inside
anything surprise you not what you
expected when you see how things work on
a production of shows so one that I did
not expect and go ahead found and still
find a very very satisfying is that it's
really a team effort there are the hosts
work together very well with lots of
communication going on between the
between the hosts as mediated by you
obviously and that small you know trying
to go to gay favors with you here I
really enjoy the way that the hosts talk
to each other because there's always
been a feedback going on about the
possible possible topics and the actual
questions to ask that people add their
own ideas this is something that I would
find interesting I didn't expect that I
was very positively surprised by that I
also think there's a there's a lot more
preparation in general going into the
show's then it's the case with many
other podcasts as far as I know at least
I'd like to give you a chance to mention
your book I know we have a lot of
listening audience in the German
language zone so many of them might want
to read it so it's called a rest
ins HTTP arrest and HTTP it has has had
two editions all right
either the second one without it has
another print or a while because working
on the third one for a long time now and
then we are actually in the process of
finishing so by the time you listen to
this podcast might actually have been
sent to the editor already and it covers
obviously rest representational state
transfer the architectural side of the
web great well thank you so much Stefan
for being on the show again thanks for
having me my next guest is Brian Brannon
who has a number of editorial
responsibilities for I Triple E Computer
Society Brian welcome to the show hey
glad to be a rubber start with my
standard question where do you live live
in beautiful huntington beach california
source to the USA and what is your job
or jobs with I Triple E well I have a
few I'm the lead editor for our Tripoli
software magazine which sponsors the SU
radio I'm also lead editor for a Tripoli
computer graphics and applications and I
Tripoli internet computing I also do the
multi medium the multimedia editor for
our computer magazine and I Triple E
software and then I staff managing
editor for se Radio for all the content
you deal with how does it break down
roughly in a pie chart between different
media types like print online text audio
video it varies from week to week and
day to day I'm just what's coming in but
from my own if you broke it down on how
much time I spend on each one and I'd
say it's around these days maybe 40
percent print and then 60 percent
multimedia to include SC radio so tell
us about your involvement with software
engineering radio the podcast sure arm
see we were approached by Marcus voltar
here at software magazine on two or
three years ago to take over publishing
SC radio he had been doing it for
many years and just out of a labor of
love as as did most of the or all of the
people involved with it and it just I
think got to be too much this it's a lot
of work as you well know and so he
approached software magazine about us
taking over the administrative and
editing responsibilities and we were
glad to do it because it fits really
well with the subject matter of software
magazine we have the show editors who as
under Marcus are volunteers and they
record the shows what are the steps that
you're involved in in taking a show from
recorded to published well it's um it
depends on the host but for the most
part go through and look at the audio
levels and make sure that they're
they're fairly balanced between the host
and the guests so that one's not louder
than the other and do any edits that are
necessary ad pumpers at the front and
back size it so it's not too big but
still good enough quality and go ahead
and send it to iTunes and post it to the
SD radio home page great so I thank you
and your team for everything you do
glad to do it talking now with Diomedes
Pinellas he made us welcome to the show
nice to be here where do you live do you
- I live in Athens Greece that's a
wonderful country located in the by the
military machine southeast in Europa and
you are part of the I Triple E Computer
Society what is your role there I'm the
editor in chief of a Tripoli software &
magazine aiming computer practitioner so
trying to create give practical advice
from theory I believe many of our
listeners have been with the show since
before the show became part of I Triple
E Computer Society and may not be
familiar with the Computer Society would
you tell us a little bit about what that
is and what its mission is and why does
it make sense for you to be a sponsor of
the show sure I Triple E
Computer Society is a professional body
from I Tripoli i triple e stands for
Institute of Electrical and Electronic
engineers it's a professional
association and performed a long time
ago combining the American Institute of
Electrical Engineers with its top radio
engineers so it see where it comes from
and it's the largest Association of
technical professional so it has more
about a half a million members from
around the world and its objectives are
to advance the educational and technical
advancement in engineering Computer
Engineering telecommunications and
similar disciplines so the Computer
Society is part of the I Triple E which
in turn wants to advance theory practice
application of computer and IT science
technology and the a major part of it is
the professional standing of its members
it is the largest of the 38 technical
societies that are part of the edge of
lis what is the relationship between the
computer society and software
engineering radio the podcast I took the
Computer Society sponsors workshops
conferences and publishes a lot of peer
review literature including the I Triple
E software magazine the software
engineering radio is affiliated with I
Triple E software because they share
common views and objectives we've been
talking now about I Triple E I want to
find out more about you what is your
your job with I Triple E that's not your
only job you have at least one other job
is that right right I'm a professor at
the Department of management science and
technology at the Athens University of
Economics and business there at each
software engineering programming tell
undergraduate course and also have a
postgraduate course on big data business
analytics quite I teach engineering big
data systems I also do research on soft
engineering mainly by using data from
software repositories from large
software repositories on big data
engineering from the system's side and
on IT security great well thank you for
that feedback and thank you very much
for speaking to the show is there
anything else you wanted listeners to
know before we wrap up
No thank you very much Robert for
hosting me my next guest is Forrest
shawl Forrest welcome to the show
thanks from our great to be here why
don't you tell us about your regular job
first ah that's a good one well my
regular job is I work for Carnegie
Mellon University and specifically for a
Institute within the university called
the software engineering Institute we're
a federally funded research and
development center so a lot of what we
do is work with we work with industry
but mainly we work with government and
primarily with the Department of Defense
trying to help them with software
acquisition software development any
software intensive system that they're
building clearly there's a role for us
there so a lot of what we do is you know
I always think of it as work in the
public good but we're trying to make
making sure that the taxpayer investment
for the folks in the u.s. at least could
spend the right way that we can help the
Department of Defense and other
government agencies built these
incredibly sophisticated in many cases
systems that they need to deal with the
challenges of today and talk about your
other job or roles that you've had would
die triploid Computer Society over a
period of years
sure well for the last four years I was
editor-in-chief of one of the
publication's of the Computer Society
slipped out and that's I Triple E
software and to my mind that was such a
great experience because software the
magazine has this kind of unique mandate
of being the bridge between research and
practice so a lot of what the content
that we featured in the magazine was all
these latest things that are coming out
of the research and academic world but
conveyed in a sense for the in a way
that's understandable for the
practitioners that should be getting
some value out of it you're there at the
time and you're involved in the show
becoming part of the magazine tell us
the story of that sure well one of the
things we did on the magazine was have
an advisory board so either we had a lot
of kind of thought leaders from across
industry across the world you know we
were very globally focused then because
we wanted to make sure that the content
we were featuring in the magazine was
relevant you know that we were getting
the right topics that we weren't missing
out on them some
topic that people in the software
industry would need to know about so one
of those advisory board members or is
Marcus halter who was the original
founder of FC radio and we happened to
have him on the board at a time when he
was looking at looking to move on to new
new tasks you know he had been doing se
radio for for a while
I won't even venture a guess I don't
remember how long he'd been doing it but
felt like he wanted to shake things up a
little bit and try some new things for
himself but of course he didn't want an
SC radio to go away because it was such
a wonderful resource for the community
so given that was his interest that one
of the things that we were able to work
out was a way by which the Computer
Society and I Triple E software in
particular kind of took over the
responsibility for SC radio and the
Marcus moved off and some of the old
team moved off we were very happy that
some of the team stayed on and we've
been trying to get some new faces new
folks on the team and you know so we had
a little bit of a transition period
there where we were trying to make sure
that the things would work out well and
we were so desperately trying to keep
the quality where Marcus had left it
because he had bequeathed us such a
wonderful resource and so I've them you
know I always say Robert that I've been
very happy when when we got connected
again with you and you kind of took up
either the mantle there and started to
put the team together and put some more
energy behind it because I think that
it's now you're we're moving along in a
way that was very much it's upon to go
with Marcus's original vision for it
great well thank you so much for talking
to the show for us oh my pleasure
my next guest is our newest host Spain
Johann spend welcome to the show hi tell
us where you live and what do you do for
work I live in Amsterdam and I work for
a company called try fog try fog is
mostly known for the go-to and queuing
conferences but we also do all kinds of
other things for instance lots of mobile
development but also Java spring
elasticsearch Conservancy how did you
first learn about the podcast
yeah I actually cannot remember when and
where but I think it was almost from the
beginning in 2006 and 2007 and I was
almost addicted I listened to almost
every show and I used to travel a lot
during that time and for me the the
software engineering radio was a perfect
opportunity to learn about the latest
and greatest new things just by
listening in the train or in the plane
so for me that was a big help and big
fun
so besides learning about new things
what else did you like about the show
the most interesting thing about the
show for me was the deep dive with let's
say the famous people on the topic one
thing I can remember in particular was
an interview with Martin odorous kion
Scala and I did a little bit Scala
course I think a couple of weeks before
this interview and a lot of things he
said in this interview
you never heard hear about it if you
take a course or if you read a book
lots of the rationale behind things why
he did stuff like he did it in Scala and
I think that's that's in general an
interesting thing about the show that
people talk about their technology or
their method or you name it but you can
dive deep and ask the questions which
are probably not published elsewhere
okay we're close to wrapping up is there
anything else you would like the
listeners to know about you
I attended two words to say that I have
a bit addicted these kind of things like
conferences and meetups and even
something like soap engineering radio
which helps people to learn or get new
ideas so for me if I think together with
the conference's is of engineering radio
really a nice opportunity to only help
myself but also do something good for
other people and thank you for speaking
to the program you're welcome
my next guest is Jeff Meyerson Jeff
welcome into software engineering radio
thanks Robert
I'll tell the listeners a little bit
about yourself so I grew up in Austin
Texas and I went to UT for computer
science for that time I spent some time
in high school and early on in college
playing a lot of poker and then in
college after here I studied computer
science it took some did some
internships and then now I'm just
working full time in the software
industry and where do you work I were
gonna Amazon right now how long have you
been with this show and what has it been
like being a host I think I've been with
the show for a a year and a half or so
at this point me it made me almost two
years and it's been really fun and
interesting it's been a good window into
learning about technologies that are
relevant in the industry in areas where
I'm not currently working a lot of times
and you learn when you're when you're
doing episodes you learn how to
communicate with people about technical
topics that you don't understand which
is definitely a valuable skill to
develop and it's a really fun way to
develop it because you get to talk to
people that really know what they're
talking about and and you get to learn a
lot how did you first find out about
this show and then how did that lead to
becoming a host so I first started
listening to the show when I would
listen to podcasts on the way to work
lore when I was exercising and I found
it I think an on the iTunes Store just
looking so I think I probably search
software or software engineering and
there are not a whole lot of good
podcasts devoted to software so it was
pretty easy you know find this one that
was you know there's high standards and
high production value so yeah well I
mean once I did once I started listening
to it
I didn't initially really know what a
lot of the stuff they were talking about
was but it it definitely taught me a lot
and then I got interested
I'm sorry what was the second part of
your question how did that lead to you
becoming a host on this show I think
what led to me becoming a host was it
was my last year of school and I was
starting to interview for a lot of jobs
I I liked podcasts a lot and I guess
maybe I started thinking about how I
could get involved or how I could do my
my own podcast perhaps and I would say
that the you know there are a lot of
benefits to doing it you know but the I
would say the biggest benefit that is
maybe underappreciated is I mean first
of all if you're doing podcasts where
you're interacting with anybody then it
gives you another social outlet and you
know software engineering radio is cool
because if we have a community of hosts
that are really interesting and good to
talk to and then we all but we also have
you know it gives you access and social
credibility to talk to you know people
that are at the top of the industry so
yeah what has driven me to it was the
ability to socialize with people great
thank you very much Jeff my next guest
is johannes tennis johannes welcome to
the show hi my standard questions for
everyone are where do you live and what
do you do for work so I live in Germany
right up in the rows in Hamburg and I do
software consulting for a living so I'm
a software developer as on the man part
and on the other part I try to help our
client adopt agile by showing them how a
good agile software developer does agile
in his day-to-day life and kind of
leading by example is our idea is agile
process one of your main interests for
the show it's definitely a part of it so
I'm very interesting in in giving agile
the or using agile to make the software
I I deliver better to better care to the
end users need and I'm always interested
in in the practices which which help
improve the software engineering process
especially a retrospective are like my
my baby topic in there
how it come about that you became a host
on the show so se radio was nearly the
first podcast I I listened to and I
really liked the format so I created a
podcast which was similar to se radio
way back when I was still studying
medical informatics and yeah this was
for the students in my university
one-hour interview podcast with
professors and and other students doing
interesting PhD theses and so when
Marcus tweeted about looking for hosts I
thought well maybe I should now play
with the big guys and and start working
with a real se radio after I stopped
doing the stuff because I stopped
studying you're involved in German
language podcast I know you went to a
conference about podcasting in Germany
whoa what was that conference like so
this German conference is these the so
called pot laughs podcasting workshop
which is so the pot life stuff is is
something around WordPress to make
podcasting easier it was quite
interesting because a lot of the German
language podcast came there and talked
there and in German especially in Berlin
there is kind of a scene of people doing
podcast and referencing each other and
doing to each other's podcast and all of
that yeah it's really interesting
because people who do podcast especially
people who do podcasts who are not
interview podcast but they're like
telling their own stories maybe talking
about their life because they are
transsexual or because they have
something else special they want to
share with the community they're quite
outspoken they have an opinion they tell
you something and that's quite
interesting were you able to contribute
anything from doing this show to the
other people at the conference that
would help them with their shows I
actually gave a little session about how
we do feedback in there in the
preparation of an interview and also how
we do feedback afterwards because I
guess a lot of people don't get any
feedback for what they're doing
especially if it's a small show which
has only like 100 listeners and I also
also showed like how our processes and
how we
because we attend hosts and we have the
luxury of at least those ten hosts very
closely looking at what you have been
doing and how you could improve what
you're doing from a perspective of
having done an interview as as well when
you're doing an interview what is it
that you're trying to bring to the
listeners and what would you want them
to take away from having listened to one
of your shows so the idea for me is you
get an overview like yeah maybe not a
10,000 foot overview but but a 1,000
foot overview of the topic that you know
kind of okay micro-service is this in
that so you split up into small services
and a few people have tried it
successfully and you have ideas what it
could mean and you also have the the
Google search terms in mind when you
really want to use it in your project to
me listening to podcasts is really good
at building knowledge like a general
knowledge you're not getting an expert
by listening to a podcast but you have
heard everything already and when you
ever need it in your project you're
prepared for that yeah I get that it's
like having signposts to what's going on
in the world of software and where you
might want to go next
are you involved in any other blogs
conferences books anything you'd like
the listeners to follow up with I have a
block which is j2 news net which I
should do more often but I didn't get to
it because I was doing so much as
podcast last year I also have a podcast
called directly here which is a German
language podcast and we do all kinds of
stuff on how to improve yourself you're
working or your organization kind of
business topics but also very
psychologic and in recent times you
could follow up on that or find me on
Twitter what's your favorite podcast
that you listen to other than software
engineering radio there is one very very
good German podcast called eternity
flows which is two guys talking about
politically / technical topics very
detailed with a lot of experience
unfortunate
they really really rarely publish so
handsome minute is a good one which is
which has kind of the same topic then we
have in English or if you if you want to
listen to some German guys trying to
podcast in English you could listen to
news of the world news with that which
is a show about yeah what is what is
going on in the world which the news are
not reporting on kind of great oh thank
you your house for being on the show
Thanks my next guest on the show is Josh
long Josh welcome to the show thank you
thank you very much what how to link one
of my standard questions is where do you
live but I'm going to answer that you
live in San Francisco pretty close to me
and my other standard question is what
do you do for work I am the developer
advocate for the open toe spring
technologies at pivotal so it's going to
ask you with all of the other media and
outreach you do is part of your job
what's different for you about
podcasting and why did you want to add
that to your repertory so podcasting
specifically as it concerns su radio not
generally obviously su radio is this
incredible opportunity to connect with
people that I tend to bump into a lot
anyway and it's just a great place to
sort of have those discussions and have
an exercise to have those you know have
some some sort of framework to have
those discussions with really
interesting people I've been very lucky
I get to talk to a lot of interesting
people and I feel like if I could just
share those people and those sessions
with others I think that actually very
useful se radio shares a lot of
interesting discussions with me you know
in that I get to listen to it I get to
spend an hour with all these really
great minds and personalities so now I
should just be nice to share share my
live whatever I can offer back out would
like to and when you do a show what is
it you're trying to bring to the
listeners with each show I want
listeners to feel that giddy a sense of
inspiration that I get when I listen to
some of these really amazing people and
as you know you know I have had these
discussions around one particular show
and that is actually something that was
driven out of turmoil or I suppose you
could even call it politics and that's
another thing I would like to be able to
kind of know
like to build a crack open you know and
share with others is to provide that
backseat you know back backstage access
to certain events in the industry and
this gives me again that's another
framework to do it great Josh well
thanks for being on the show and thanks
for doing shows thank you very very much
for having me I'm truly honored
listeners may not know but I've just
started this journey on the TV do so
yeah I'm honored thank you very much
Thank You Josh thanks for listening to
se Radio an educational program brought
to you by I Triple E software magazine
for more information about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website at se - radioman to provide
feedback you can write comments on each
episode on the website or write a review
on itunes mention a message us on
twitter at se radio or search for the
software engineering radio group on
LinkedIn Google+ or Facebook you can
also email us at team at se - radio net
this and all other episodes of SU radio
is licensed under the creative commons
two-point-five license thanks again for
your support
[Applause]
[Music]
you